学生们好
hello students
我是Yan，这个视频是对沙盒模块的一个介绍
I'm Yan and this is the introduction to the sandboxing module of pwn College
这个模块会讲到
and this module will talk about
沙盒的概念
the concept of sandboxing
沙盒使用到的技术和
the technologies used in sandboxing and
从简单沙盒中逃逸的方法
the ways to break out of at least kind of rudimentary sandboxes
让我们来谈谈沙盒
so let's talk about sandboxing
这是什么意思呢
what do we mean by this
这有一个XKCD漫画介绍了沙箱发展的循环（xkcd指Randall Munroe的网名或者他的漫画）
there's a relevant xkcd as there's for a lot of things about the sandboxing cycle
本质上，新技术可以以很酷的方式和系统组合在一起，实现很酷的功能
essentially as we develop new technology that can be put together in cool ways to enable cool functionality
但慢慢地我们开始意识到
we start slowly realizing
我们对这项技术的使用方式
that the way that we have put this technology together
不是很安全
is not very secure
导致很多漏洞等等
causes a lot of vulnerabilities etcetera
这种情况一次又一次地发生在不同的技术中
and this happens time and time again with different technologies
然后我们会想出其他方法来分离它们或者使用沙盒
and then we end up figuring out other ways to either separate them or to sandbox
本质上是为了将这些漏洞的能力降低到对系统无害的程度
essentially to reduce the ability of these vulnerabilities to harmless in these systems
好吧，让我们回到最初的起点
all right let's let's rewind back to the beginning
我们会以十年为单位的讲
we're just gonna do a decade by decade jump
这里的十年是大概的
these decades are very approximate
这只是一个很好的框架
it's just a good frame
不要把这当成是对计算机历史的准确描述（防杠声明）
don't don't take this as kind of verbatim the history of computing
但是让我们看一下
but let's go through and look at
沙盒的起源
how kind of sandboxing arose
起初
from the beginning or close to the beginning
20世纪50年代的计算机
which is computers back at let's say the 1950s
这些电脑用打卡器写程序
right these computers you often wrote programs with Sam punch cards
当你把这些程序加载到电脑里
and when you loaded these programs into the computer
它们会在裸机里运行
they would just run in the like bare metal of the computer just
最接近硬件
as close to the hardware
计算机唯一做的事情就是执行你的程序
that was the only thing the computer was doing was executing your program
问题是，有很多问题
the problem it was was, there were multiple problems
一是一次只能执行一个程序
one is could execute only one program at a time
二是这些程序可能会破坏硬件等等
the programs could do stuff like damage the hardware and so forth
他们可以在机器上做任何事情
they could do anything on the machine
某些操作的副作用很危险
and certain things had side effects that could be dangerous
所以
and so
给操作系统和用户空间做了隔离
the split of kind of an operating system in the user space arose which
它做了两件事。一是提供了更多的保护
did 2 things they enabled a bit more Protection
比如一个普通进程在跑的时候计算机不会破坏它
so a typical process running and your machine couldn't destroy it
二是允许同时运行多个进程
and 2 they allowed multiple processes to run at the same time
所以我们慢慢开始开发多进程系统
so we slowly started developing multi processed systems
每个进程都可以运行
where every process could run
但要避免与其他进程冲突
as long as it carefully avoided collaboring other processes
在非常早期的原型中
right in very early prototypes you could you know
一个进程和一部分内存空间对应
have one process and one part of the memory space
另一个进程和另一部分内存空间对应
another process and another part of the memory space
他们只会使用自己的那部分内存空间，避免相互冲突
and they would happily use their own part of that memory space  to avoid collaborating each other
问题是，如果人们不小心，他们就会相互冲突
the problem is that they could collaborate each other if the people weren't careful
所以人们创造了一种沙盒
and so they created essentially a sort of sandboxing
将这些进程分隔到它们自己的内存空间中
that we separated these processes into their own memory spaces
我们创建了虚拟内存
we created virtual memory
现在你接触的大多数电脑
nowadays um most computers you interact with
都支持虚拟内存
will have virtual memory support
多个进程都有自己的内存视图
where multiple processes will have their own view of memory um
所以他们不会相互冲突
so they don't collaborate each other
然后其他的隔离和沙盒措施开始出现
uh and then other um kind of isolation and sandboxing measures um start arising
在90年代，再次声明这是一个近似的描述
uh let's say in the 90s again this is kind of a um approximating frame and
90年代出现了脚本语言
the 90s you see the creation of uh scripting languages
嗯
um
而且
and
脚本语言在解释器和脚本代码之间有一个隐式的隔离
scripting languages have a implicit separation between the interpreter and the interpreted thing  right the interpreted code
解释器会执行底层操作
and the interpreter has you know low level operations that it does and so forth
脚本代码只是调用解释器
the interpreter code just calls into the interpreter
这是一种隔离
it's a sort of isolation
它本意不是为了安全
that is not meant to be a security isolation
但实际上却经常被这样用
but is often actually utilized as such
有很多在线服务会
there are plenty of online services that will
给你一个Python shell来玩
give you like a Python shell to play around with
每隔一段时间，由于Python代码和Python解释器之间的错误隔离
and every once in a while because of faulty isolation between Python the interpreter language and Python the interpreter
安全问题产生了
security of own abilities arise
这方面有一些著名的例子
and there are some famous examples of this
例如在
for example on
微软的Rise for fun平台
Microsoft's Rise for fun platform
它允许你在那个平台上直接与Python交互
which allowed you to interact directly with Python within that platform
但由于安全问题，这个功能不得不被取消了一段时间
but that functionality had to be taken down for a while specifically because of security issues
让我们看一个具体的例子来为这个模块做个提升
let's look at a specific case of this to motivate this module
那就是网页浏览器
and that is web browsers
Web浏览器可能是最大的例子
web browsers are probably the biggest example
所有潜在的功能都被塞进了一个程序
of all potential functionality being stuffed into one program
以满足快速扩张的网络需求
to keep up with the needs of a rapidly expanding web
在21世纪初
in the early 2000s
我们看到YouTube的崛起
we saw the rise of YouTube
甚至比它更早的内容创作平台，比如其它的视频分享网站，游戏平台
the rise of even earlier than that  other video sharing and sharing of you know game creation platforms
有很多丰富的网络内容
a lot of rich web content and
这些都是由Adobe Flash、 ActiveX、 Java applet之类的东西提供支持
these was powered by things such as Adobe Flash Active X Java applets
这些都拥有运行浏览器时的用户的完整权限
these sort of technologies that all ran in your browser with the full permissions of the user you were running them on
使用完整的权限丰富了网页的内容和功能
as the full privileges to enable rich content on the web
最后导致拥有了狂野西部世界般的安全性
what ended up happening was kind of the Wild West of security
新的漏洞不断被发现
you had new vulnerabilities constantly being discovered
这些漏洞将使攻击者基本上完全控制您的系统
in the expectation of these vulnerabilities would give an attacker essentially full control of your system
就好像他们是你的用户一样
as if they were acting as your user
这些基本都和flash、Java applet、ActiveX有关
this happened constantly with flash constantly with Java constantly with Active X
并且
and uh
它带来了爆炸式增长并且由下载的驱动的（安全事件）
it LED to this huge explosion and drive by downloads
有一段时间他们是互联网上最大的威胁
for a while um they were the biggest threat on the Internet
你会不小心点击一个恶意链接
you would accidentally click a malicious link
它会加载一个存在漏洞的ActiveX控件
it would load an ActiveX control that would have a vulnerability
然后你
and then you
你的机器就被感染了
it would be over your machine is infected
嗯
um
所以
so
最初的缓解措施是试图消除
initial mitigations into this was trying to eliminate
漏洞软件，减少攻击面
vulnerable software reduced the attack surface
就是打补丁
patch bugs of course
Adobe Flash没有在这种方法中幸存下来
Adobe Flash for example didn't survive this sort of mitigation
它死了的原因有很多，其中一部分是它的安全状况
it was killed off and for many reasons part of them is the security posture of that
系统ActiveX也被淘汰
system Active X was eliminated
Java applets 在现在的互联网上也看不到了
Java applets are not something you see on Internet nowadays
再次声明，这不仅仅是因为安全问题，
again not just because of security but
但安全问题是部分原因
but also in part because of security
现在你看到的大多数Java applet都是遗留系统
nowadays most Java applet you see are legacy systems that
有些公司可能会在内部使用
some companies might use internally
但他们会碰到很多困难最终
then they would actually go through a lot of jump through a lot of hoops to actually
让它们在一个合理的浏览器中工作
make them work in a reasonable browser
但这并没有解决问题
but this didn't solve the problems right
当我们移除这些
as we removed these
攻击面，黑客就转移到其他区域
attack surfaces hackers moved on to other areas
为了消除
um in order to eliminate
呃
uh
Flash等等
flash and so forth
我们不得不创造了表现很好的
we had to create very performance
非常强大的Javascript引擎
very high power Javascript engines
这替代了很多我们消除了的动态网页功能
that could do a lot of this dynamic content functionality that we were eliminating
这导致
this caused
这些漏洞（口误）
these vulnerability
Javascript引擎非常复杂，有更多的漏洞
javascript engines to be very complex with more vulnerabilities
浏览器的功能代表了一些
functionality of your browser represents some
可能有漏洞的潜在表面
potential surface that could have a vulnerability
GIF解析库
the gif parsing library
浏览器使用的各种媒体数据编解码器
the various media codex that your browser uses
所有这些都有潜在的脆弱性
all of these are potentially vulnerable
并且有一些例子表明他们实际上很脆弱
and there are examples of them being actually vulnerable
这就导致了
and this causing
和以前一样的问题
the same problem as before
和利用Adobe Flash时同样的问题又
the exact same problem is when you would exploit Adobe Flash
发生在你利用Javascript即时编译器中的漏洞时
occurs when you exploit a vulnerability in your Javascript Just in time compiler
这就导致了
and so this led and now this is
近代史中浏览器沙箱的兴起
you know very recent history to the rise of sandboxing in the browser
这个想法是任何代码数据和
the idea being that any code data and
提醒一下代码和数据大致相同的东西
as a reminder code and data roughly the same thing
任何您不信任的代码和数据都应该以基本为0的权限运行
any code and data that you don't trust should run with basically 0 privileges
通常是这样实现的
the way that this is generally accomplished
在现代浏览器中有一个进程
you have a process let's say on a modern browser
它有一个父进程，负责与系统交互
you have a parent process that is responsible for interacting with your system
这个父进程有对应的权限
and has the privileges to do so
但是每一个
but then every single
页面、插件和扩展
individual page and individual plugin and individual extension
它们都运行在自己的进程中，没有权限
they all run in their own processes with no privileges
如果一个进程
if a process
如果某个沙盒中的子进程需要对系统做些事
if one of these individual child sandboxed processes needs to do something to the system
比如存一个cookie
store a cookie
显示一些内容等
display some content something along these lines
它会要求父进程代表它去做
it'll ask the parent process to do it that on its behalf
这是理想的模型
this is the ideal model
事情并不总是这样的
it's not always how things work
出于性能考虑
for performance reasons
通常
oftentimes
这些子进程必须与整个系统进行通信，等等
these child processes have to talk to the system at large and so forth
但这是理想的沙盒场景
um but this is the ideal sandbox scenario
在这个模块中，我们将学习
and in this module we will learn
不同沙盒的工作原理。(我们)会简单的讲
how different sandboxes work. (we) will keep things simple
这不是沙盒设计课程
um this isn't a sandbox design course
这是一门网络安全概览课程
this is a a a Cyber Security Overview course
我们将主要研究简单的沙盒
we will look at simple sandboxes for the most part
还有一些现代沙盒技术
but also some modern sandboxing techniques
最后是关于沙盒有效性的说明
finally a note on sandbox effectiveness
正确的
right
我讲了很多关于沙盒的事情，它是如何崛起的
I talk a lot about sandboxing what it is how to rose
有用吗?
does it work
是的，它很管用
yes it works a lot
在这门课中我们会看到
throughout this course we look at
有几个缓解措施非常有力
several mitigations that are extremely strong
强缓解措施针对它的目标漏洞
a strong mitigation is something that  for the vulnerability class that it is designed to mitigate against
从本质上大大提高了安全性
essentially raises the bar significantly
沙盒就是这样
sandboxing does this uh
在2000年早期
whereas in the early 2 thousands
你只需要一个Adobe Flash的代码执行漏洞
you needed one vulnerability code execution in Adobe Flash
就能在受害者电脑里横冲直撞
to um rampage across victims computer
现在你需要更多，你需要Javascript JIT编译器的漏洞
nowadays you need more you need vulnerability in your Javascript Justin Time compiler
和
and
沙盒漏洞、内核漏洞或者是脆弱进程漏洞
vulnerability in the sandbox or the kernel or something around  the vulnerable process
所以你先在沙盒里站稳脚跟，然后
so you first get a foothold inside the sandbox and then
你还得逃逸出沙盒
you have to escape that sandbox and in this module
在本模块中，我们将研究如何在简单沙盒中做到这点
in this module that's what we will be looking at how to do for very simple sandboxes
以后的视频见
see you later in future videos